Guide to the Bapsi Sidhwa papers, 1943-2018 MS 885
Woodson Research Center, Rice University, Houston, Texas
Bapsi Sidhwa papers
1943-2018
Woodson Research Center, Rice University, Houston, Texas https://library.rice.edu/woodson
Sidhwa, Bapsi
MS 885
14 Linear Feet 4 Boxes
The Bapsi Sidhwa papers comprise the books, drafts, notes, and personal papers of the acclaimed American-Pakistani author Bapsi Sidhwa. Known for her captivating novels exploring mainly women's issues in the Indian subcontinent, Bapsi has made her mark with her deeply insightful prose and outspoken voice.
Biographical / Historical
Born August 11, 1938 to Gujarati Parsi Zoroastrian parents Peshotan and Tehmina Bhandara, Bapsi Sidhwa is an American–Pakistani novelist whose books, including "The Crow Eaters," "The Pakistani Bride," "Cracking India," and "An American Brat," have gained international acclaim for their exploration of the identity issues of Pakistani Parsi immigrants to the US, their life-styles and their culture.
After she was born, Bapsi's parents moved from Karachi to the city of Lahore, a large influence on Bapsi's later writing. Bapsi contracted polio at the age of two, and was nine at the time of the Partition--both events shaped her later writing, especially through the character of Lenny in "Ice Candy Man." In 1957, Bapsi received her BA from Kinnaird College for Women in Lahore. She married at the age of 19 and moved to Bombay for five years before she divorced and remarried in Lahore with her second husband Noshir Sidhwa. She had three children in Pakistan before beginning her career as an author.
Bapsi is perhaps best known for her collaborative work with Indo-Canadian filmmaker Deepa Mehta; Her novels "Ice Candy Man (1991)" and "Water: A Novel" formed the basis for the latter two films in Mehta's "Elements" Trilogy, "Earth," and "Water." In addition to her novels, Bapsi has written essays and reviews for publications, and travelled for speaking engagements, spending a great deal of time abroad before settling in Houston. Bapsi has also taught at Columbia University, University of Houston, Mount Holyoke College, Southampton University, and Brandeis.
Bapsi's work focuses especially on improving the struggles of women in the Indian subcontinent, and she served on the advisory committee to Prime Minister Benazir Bhutto on Women's Development in pursuit of that goal. Among her many honors, Bapsi received the Bunting Fellowship at Radcliffe/Harvard, the Lila Wallace-Reader's Digest Writer's Award, the Sitara-i-Imtiaz (Pakistan's highest national honor in the arts), the LiBeraturepreis in Germany, and the 2007 Primo Mondello Award in Italy.
Scope and Contents
The Bapsi Sidhwa papers contain materials related to Bapsi's writing, such as manuscripts, drafts, and contracts and correspondence with the publishers of her several books. Also contained in the collection are Bapsi's essays, articles, reviews, and lecture notes from speaking events. Many of Bapsi's published books, often with personal commentary and notes written in, can also be found in the collection. A large portion of the papers are devoted to the press surrounding Bapsi's work--including reviews, articles, and interviews from America, the United Kingdom, India, and Pakistan. Lastly, a section of the collection contains materials related to Bapsi's family life, including correspondence, newspaper clippings, and photographs.
The materials are in good condition and range in date from 1943 to 2018. Researchers interested in Women's Issues, the Indian Partition, Bapsi's relationships with family, friends, and acquaintances, and particularly the process of writing Bapsi's novels, will find this collection enlightening.
Conditions Governing Access
This material is restricted. Stored off-site at the Library Service Center and requires 24-hour notice for retrieval. Please contact the Woodson Research Center at 713-348-2586 or woodson@rice.edu for more information.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The materials were donated by Mohur Sidhwa in September of 2018.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged in five series, as follows:
Series I: Writings
Series II: Events and Related Research
Series III: PUblishing Materials
Series IV: Press
Series V: Personal Files
Series VI: Books
Index Terms
Subjects
Women; Newspapers; Literature; Social life and customs
Document Types
manuscripts (document genre); essays; articles; reviews (document genre); notes; lecture notes; interviews; letters (correspondence); personal correspondence; legal documents; photographs; slides (photographs); invitations; brochures; books
Places
Asian Americans
- Series I: Writings
  - Sub-Series A: Manuscripts
    - "Zaitoon" / "A Pakistani Bride", 1969 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - "Zaitoon" / "A Pakistani Bride", 1975 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - "Zaitoon", n.d. (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - "The Jungle Wallas", n.d. (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - "The Bride" (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - "The Bride" (Jonathan Cape Ltd.) (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Sub-Series B: Drafts
    - "The American Brat", May 1992 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - "The American Brat" (3rd-to-last version) (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - "The American Brat" (1/2) (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - "The American Brat" (2/2) (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - "The American Brat" (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - "The American Brat" (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - "Ice-Candy-Man" First Draft (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - "Ice-Candy-Man" (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - "Ice-Candy-Man" (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Scene from "Ice-Candy-Man" Original (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Gujarati transcription of scene from "Ice-Candy-Man" (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - "Language of Love" (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Articles by Bapsi Sidhwa (1/2) (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Articles by Bapsi Sidhwa (2/2) (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Essays and Interviews by Bapsi Sidhwa (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Reviews written by Bapsi Sidhwa, 1984-1999 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Unpublished Writings by Bapsi Sidhwa (Box 2, Folder 11)
- Series II: Events and Related Research
  - Lila Wallace Reader's Digestt Awards Lecture Series, Organized by Bapsi in collaboration with the Asia Society (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Speaking Events and Lectures, 1988-2016 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Convention on the Elimination of All Forms of Discrimination Against Women, 1979 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Women's Rights Research and Writings (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Writings about Taslima Nasreen (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - "Women in Pakistan" Research (Box 2, Folder 17)
- Series III: Publishing Materials
  - Book Covers / Graphics (Box 3)
  - Sub-Series A: Publisher Info
    - Author Marketing Experts, Inc., 2012 (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - Fontana Publishing ("The Crow Eaters") (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - Jonathan Cape, 1981-1996 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Milkweed, 1990-2013 (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - Neri Pozza (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Penguin, 1988-2007 (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - Penguin ("Their Language of Love"), 2011, 2013 (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - Peters, Fraser, & Dunlap Agency (UK) (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - St. Martin's Press ("The Crow Eaters") (Box 3, Folder 10)
    - Sterling Lord Literistic, Inc. (Box 3, Folder 11)
    - Sterling Lord Literistic, Inc. (Italian) (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Sub-Series B: Adaptations
    - "An American Brat" Play Adaptation reviews, March, 2007 (Box 3, Folder 13)
    - "The Bride" film paperwork, 2006-2012 (Box 3, Folder 14)
    - "The Crow Eaters" film paperwork, 2001-12-12 (Box 3, Folder 15)
    - "Earth" film paperwork, photos, press (Box 3, Folder 16)
    - "Earth" movie slides & slide list, 1999-01-06 (Box 3, Folder 17)
    - "Feroza" / "Sock 'em with Honey" play press, graphics, correspondence, April 2003 (Box 3, Folder 18)
    - "Water" film paperwork (Box 3, Folder 19)
    - "You Can Make Your Dreams Work" Contract, 2011-11-03 (Box 3, Folder 20)
- Series IV: Press
  - Sub-Series A: Interviews
    - India, 1943-2000 (Box 3, Folder 21)
    - Pakistan, 1980-1999
    - U.S.A, 1990-2015 (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - Sub-Series B: Reviews
    - "An American Brat" Reviews: India, 1991-1996 (Box 3, Folder 24)
    - "The Bride" Reviews: United Kingdom, 1983-1984 (Box 3, Folder 25)
    - "The Bride" Reviews: U.S.A., 1983-1995 (Box 3, Folder 26)
    - "The Crow Eaters" Reviews: United Kingdom, 1980-1994 (Box 3, Folder 27)
    - "The Crow Eaters" Reviews: U.S.A, 1982 (Box 3, Folder 28)
    - Reviews: India, 1984-1998 (Box 3, Folder 29)
  - Sub-Series C: Articles
    - Articles on Bapsi Sidhwa, 1978-2014 (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - Pakistan Articles (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - United Kingdom Articles (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - U.S.A Articles (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - Mixed Articles (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - Articles on Related Topics or People (Box 4, Folder 6)
- Series V: Personal Files
  - Sub-Series A: Family Files
    - Minoo Bhandara (Bapsi's Brother), 1986-1999 (Box 4, Folder 7)
    - Shri Peshota Bhandara (Bapsi's Father) (Box 4, Folder 8)
    - Tehmina Bhandara (Bapsi's Mother), 1988, 1997 (Box 4, Folder 9)
    - Bapsey Gustad Irani (Deed of Trust) (Box 4, Folder 10)
    - Mohur Sidhwa Legal Papers (Box 4, Folder 11)
    - Noshir Sidhwa (Bapsi's 2nd Husband) (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Sub-Series B: Correspondence
    - Letters of Appointment & Reccomendation, 1985-1998 (Box 4, Folder 13)
    - Letters of Rejection, 1972-1985 (Box 4, Folder 14)
    - Anita Desai (Box 4, Folder 15)
    - Editors (Box 4, Folder 16)
    - Salman Rushdie (Box 4, Folder 17)
    - University Professors, 1984-2001 (Box 4, Folder 18)
    - Sub-Group A: Correspondence by Date
      - 1970s (Box 4, Folder 19)
      - 1980-1985 (Box 4, Folder 20)
      - 1986-1989 (Box 4, Folder 21)
      - 1990s (Box 4, Folder 22)
      - 2000s (Box 4, Folder 23)
      - 2010s (Box 4, Folder 24)
      - n.d. [Alphabetical] (Box 4, Folder 25)
  - Bapsi's Photographs on CD with descriptive list (Box 4, Folder 26)
  - Incomplete Itemized Lists of Content in Original Accession Boxes, 2018-09-25 (Box 4, Folder 27)
- Series VI: Books
  - "The Bapsi Sidhwa Omnibus" [Includes "The Crow Eaters", "The Bride", "Ice-Candy-Man", "An American Brat"] (Box 5)
  - "The Bride" (St. Edmundsbury Press), 1983 (Box 5)
  - "The Bride" (ILQA Publishing), 2012 (Box 5)
  - "City of Sin and Splendour" edited by Bapsi Sidhwa (Box 5)
  - "Cracking India" (Milkweed Publications), 1991 (Box 5)
  - "Cracking India" (Milkweed Publications), 2006 (Box 5)
  - "The Crow Eaters" (Penguin Publishers, India), 1990 (Box 5)
  - "The Crow Eaters" (Milkweed Publishers, USA), 1992 (Box 5)
  - "The Crow Eaters" (ILQA Publishing, Pakistan), 2015 (Box 5)
  - "Ice-Candy-Man" (Penguin Publishing, signed by the cast of "Earth"), 1989 (Box 5)
  - "Ice-Candy-Man" (Penguin Publishing, film cover), 1989 (Box 5)
  - "Ice-Candy-Man" (German translation), 1990 (Box 5)
  - "Ice-Candy-Man" (ILQA Publishing, Pakistan), 2012 (Box 5)
  - "Landscapes of Writing" (Box 5)
  - "Their Language of Love" (Box 5)
  - "Readings Companion to the Novels of Bapsi Sidhwa" (Box 5)
- Series VII: Images of donation of Bapsi Sidhwa archives
  - Images of donation of Bapsi Sidhwa archives, 2019-02